Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, good ערב שבת הגדול. Erev Shabbat Hagadol.
Today's דף daf is ע"ו, Ayin Vav, and we make a radical
shift from all of the agadic discussions and even what I would
sort of call like classic בבא בתרא Bava Batra discussions to a
סוגיא sugya that is seems like it could have come from many
other places in ש"ס. Shas. And let's take a look. It begins
about fifteen lines from the bottom, right after the two dots, first
word on the line on ע"ה עמוד ב'. Ayin Hey Amud Bet.
איתמר, Itmar, it was taught. ספינה, Sefina, so remember the boat, so
we dealt with when you sell the boat what comes with it.
So whether after a quick addressing of the words of the משנה,
mishna, of the mast and the sail and so on, we have
like three דפי dapi of אגדתא agadata about like you know about
people that go out, go to the sea, go to the ocean.
Right now we deal with the act of taking possession of a
boat. So let's see how that would be done. ספינה. Sefina. רב
אמר, Rav Amar, כיון שמשך כל שהוא קנה. kivan shemshach kol shehu
kana. So we're assuming you've acquired with משיכה, meshicha, it's מטלטלין. metaltelin.
Now of course it is an interesting question about do we look
at a boat as מטלטלין. metaltelin. I mean, you know, if you
ever go past down the what's the name of that you know
where the intrepid is, those piers there over there by the West
Side Highway, you see sometimes they have one of those cruise ships,
right? So imagine trying to do a משיכה meshicha on one of
those cruise ships. I mean, I guess if it's in the water,
but nevertheless, I think there's probably there's I think there's a lot
of inertial, you know. Like you what a donkey? You know? Yeah,
exactly. Anyway, the point I'm trying to make is that the classic
קניינים kinyanim of מטלטלין, metaltelin, right, משיכה, meshicha, הגבהה, hagbah, well we'll
see מסירה mesirah is possible handing over let's say the rope of
the boat or something, we'll talk about that and why that does
or does not come up. But you know once you get a
מטלטלין metaltelin that's a certain like type of a large size, it
seems that those are not so relevant. I mean you could always
do it with a קניין חליפין, kinyan chalipin, you know, but like
how would you really do it? You might remember the גמרא Gemara
discussed an elephant when we did קידושין, Kiddushin, like thrown be throw
a peanut to get the elephant, that doesn't work for a boat.
So anyway, so you know some types of things are so large
you would think maybe they should be like land, like you would
want to sell it with a שטר shtar or something, but you
don't. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara here discusses taking possession of
it with משיכה. meshicha. It's not immediately concerned with the size of
the boat, it's a question about technically how far do you have
to drag it? Okay, משיכה meshicha means you pull the thing towards
you. Well, how much do you have to pull it? So איתמר,
Itmar, ספינה. Sefina. רב אמר, Rav Amar, כיון שמשך כל שהוא, kivan
shemshach kol shehu, even a little bit, you displaced it like a
centimeter, okay, you moved it a little bit from where it was.
So קנה, kana, you take possession. ושמואל אמר, לא קנה עד שימשוך
את כולה. U'Shmuel Amar lo kana ad sheyimshoch es kula. You have
to completely displace it from its original location. Let me let me
let me just for משל mashal
use as a little example. Okay. So here's here's my boat. Okay,
so according to רב, Rav, there, that was the משיכה. meshicha. Okay,
I moved it a centimeter. Okay, what's according to שמואל, Shmuel, I
would have to totally remove, totally full pull its length so that
no part of it was now sitting where any part of it
had been sitting before. Okay, so let's take a look.
Let's see how you you could kind of like be in
there and like you know row it kind of. Yeah, you can
you can row it any way that you get it to move.
Okay, so you're right, it doesn't have to be by pulling it.
Okay. ושמואל אמר U'Shmuel Amar, לא קנה עד שימשוך את כולה. lo
kana ad sheyimshoch es kula. לימא כתנאי, Leima k'tannai,
let's say this follows the following debate of תנאים, Tannaim, because this
shouldn't be just a question about a boat, it should be a
general question. כיצד במסירה? Keitzad bemesirah? How are you taking possession of
animals, such an animals like large animals, you take possession with מסירה
mesirah handing over the reins, like let's say a horse or a
cow or something like that. So how do you do that? אחזה
בטלפה, Achaza b'talphah, if you held took hold of its hoof. בשערה,
Besearah,
its hair which I think means here its tail.
ובאוכף שעליה, U'ukaf she'aleha, the saddle. ובשליף שעליה, Beshalif she'aleha,
the saddle bag. בפרומביא שבפיה, Bafrombaya shebepiha,
the bit in its mouth. ובזוג שבצוארה, Bezog shebetzavara, the bell around
its neck. קנה, Kana, so whether you take physical take hold of
any part of the animal itself or anything that's connected to the
animal, that's a קניין, kinyan, that's מסירה. mesirah. Now I want to
pause for a moment because we're going to be dealing with מסירה.
mesirah. מסירה mesirah literally means handing over. And the גמרא Gemara actually
says that you cannot do מסירה mesirah with a הפקר hefker item
because there is nobody to hand it over. So what does that
mean though, because here it sounds like when you took hold of
the hoof, the other guy wasn't handing you the hoof. So there's
two opinions in תוספות. Tosfos. One says מסירה mesirah always requires that
the seller or the gifter physically hands you that thing, so actually
yes, he would have to hold the hoof and then hand it
to you and you take the hoof. The other is is that
it could be a virtual handing, not a physical handing. He would
have to say to you. you, go take, go hold on to
that hoof, go take that hoof, take and seize that hoof, and
by that you will be קונה. koneh. But the point being that
as opposed to something like הגבהה hagbahah and משיכה meshicha where it's
the physical act in itself that demonstrates ownership. I've lifted something up,
I've pulled something towards me. Here holding onto a saddle does not
demonstrate ownership by itself. Holding onto a hoof does not. Part of
what demonstrates ownership is not the physical act in itself, but the
fact that it's in the context that it was handed over. מסירה,
mesira, this part of the handing over, a part of the animal,
like, or the reins or whatever is what is symbolic of the
transferring of property. So without a seller or a gifter to hand
it over, either literally, physically or virtually, it is not a קנין.
kinyan. Okay, so that's the קנין kinyan of מסירה mesira and because
you have the context of handing over, you don't have to do
as much in terms of physically taking it to you. Yes.
Were you being literal, would he have to say hold onto a
hoof and I hold onto a hoof, or could he just say
oh yeah, take the animal?
You still see some of the specifics, but he could, it's the
מכוון mechaven of he just says לך חזק וקני. lech chazek u'kni.
It doesn't have to be that specific, but there has to be
an act, either verbal or physical, of giving it over.
Same thing with the cars. So if I drive it, that's the
same idea as משיכה? meshicha?
Yes. You do not have to drag it, you just have to
move it. Okay. So now it says like this. Okay, so that's
מסירה. mesira. This is a משנה, mishnah, this
is going back in קידושין, Kiddushin, it's a תוספתא Tosefta of קידושין
Kiddushin where קידושין Kiddushin lists the classic קניינים kinyanim and this gives
you the specifics.
כיצד במשיכה, keitzad bimeshicha, how do you do משיכה meshicha which works
on כל מטלטלין kol metaltelin and small animals and so on? קורא
לה והיא באה, koreh lah vehia ba'ah, so there you go Michael,
you see, if you wait all things are answered. You don't have
to physically drag it, you just get it to move. So you
call it, here boy, and it comes to you. או שהקישה במקל
o shehikisha bamakel or you hit it with a stick ורצתה לפניו
veratzta lefanav and it ran in front of you. כיון שעקרה יד
ורגל קנאה. keivan she'akra yad varegel kena'ah. Now this is what we're
focusing on. Fine. How far did it move? So once it lifted
up a foot and a,
fore... a foreleg? Yeah, foreleg. A foreleg and a hind leg, that's
קונה. koneh. רבי אחאי ואמרי לה רבי אחא אומר, Rabbi Achai v'amrei
lah Rabbi Acha omer, Rabbi Achai and some say Rabbi Acha says.
יד ורגל. yad varegel.
The ו vav is not...
did I say or? It's and, it's and. Yeah. עד שתהלך מלא
קומתה. ad shetehalech mlo komatah. No, it has to actually move this,
literally moves its whole height, but presumably it means, you know, displace
itself, move an entire length. Right. So that seems to be exactly
the debate of רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. Is it a little bit
of a movement or being fully displaced? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לימא רב דאמר כתנא קמא, leima Rav d'amar k'tanna kamma, Rav
who says even a small amount like the תנא קמא, tanna kamma,
just moving like a front and a back leg, ושמואל דאמר כרבי
אחא, u'Shmuel d'amar k'Rabbi Acha, and Shmuel says like Rabbi Achai, its
whole length? So it seems certainly it would seem to be what's
going on.
Even if it moves
a יד yad או רגל? o regel? Well, if it just moves
a יד, yad, it hasn't moved at all.
It's lifted up. What? It lifts up the...
Yeah, but it's not moving. It has to actually move relative to
the ground. It actually, where it is, it has to be in
a little bit of a different place. Okay, so even רב Rav
says it has to a little bit be displaced, just not fully
displaced. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר לך רב. amar lach
Rav. Of course, the thing is though if it move... even if
it moves a יד... yad... well if it moves a יד yad
ורגל, v'regel, I mean it's a little funny question, right? Because if
it moves... now I'm not the best drawer of horses, well but
now I have to draw a horse in motion. Okay, but anyway,
this is going to be awful. Anyway, okay, so here it is,
there's its front leg, this is I don't know what this looks
like, anyway. So if it moves like a יד, yad, so if
it went from... I guess we need a before and an after.
Anyway, if it moved from here to here, right, if this went
that way
and now you know this thing here went like now it's here,
right? Like what does that mean that it moved? Like I don't
know if the whole body here, I mean did it maybe a
little bit move forward? I guess where the base of it is,
I'm trying to think, like it's hard to think about that in
compared to just an inanimate object, right? I guess it moved in
that in that part of its base was here and now part
of its base is a little bit more further where it was.
So that seems to be similar to the idea of רב Rav
that it was displaced a little bit. Alright, I assume it's also
a little bit of the body moves forward, so if a little
of the body moves forward and a little bit of the base,
as it were, two of the legs moved forward, so that's considered
to be enough.
Is the element that the boat is in motion?
Yeah, that's true, but let's, let's assume that we're dealing with like
stable water, let's not, yeah, let's not sort of introduce that factor.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So let's say this
is the same debate. So the גמרא Gemara says... אמר לך רב
אנא דאמרי אפילו לרבי אחא.
amar lach Rav ana d'amri
afilu l'Rabbi Acha.
Rav, I who say a little bit by a boat, would I,
I could agree even to Rabbi Achai that by an animal you
have to... to displace it fully. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אחא
אלא בבעלי חיים. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rebbi Akha ela biv'alei chayim.
When does he say that you have to displace it fully by
an animal, when does he say that you have to displace it
fully, that's by an animal. דאף על גב דעקרא יד ורגל, De'af
al gav de'akrai yad varegel, even though it moved a front and
a hind leg, בדוכתא קיימא, beduchta kaima, this is sort of what
I was sort of getting at, it's like it's sort of really
where it always was. I mean, those two legs were sort of
where it was, it's you know it's not so obvious you say
the whole thing displaced itself a little bit, right? So so it's
basically where it was. אבל ספינה כיון דנד פורתא נד כולה, Aval
sevina keivan denad purta nad kulla, but by a boat, I think
it's even more than that, not only is, by a boat, when
I move this boat a little bit, right, forward, okay, I've only
displaced it a little bit, but every part of the boat has
been displaced from its previous location, right? You see that, right? Everything
was
in point X and now it's every single part of the boat
is in like X plus epsilon or whatever, every single part has
been displaced a little bit from its original location and there, even
though maybe this leg is moved and this leg is moved, this
leg is where it was, this leg is where it was, right,
a lot of the animal is where it always was. So therefore
you could say in this case you would need the whole animal
to move. Now the question is why would you need it to
move like okay so מלא קומתה, melo komata, its entire length. Right,
it should be enough that the whole animal took a half a
step forward. Right, all four legs moved, it took a half a
step forward, then the whole animal was displaced, so it doesn't exactly
match up. But anyway, he says by animals where it's not that
just because it moves a little does the whole animal shift, so
therefore you'd have to move the whole thing. But by a boat,
a little movement is enough.
Okay, that's a good example. How would you conceptualize it? Like what's
the difference between an animal and a boat conceptually? Right. Right. I
can't.
Yeah. Well, but I mean you understand that a, you understand that
the front and back legs don't move the entire animal, but but
if the whole animal took one step forward, I don't know why
that shouldn't be enough. Why you need מלא קומתה. melo komata.
I was going to say. What? Something to do with the חיות
chayut of the animal.
Maybe, but
that we're going to get to the next line. So let's see
the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: But okay. Anyway, by a boat you move it
a little, every part of the boat moves. ושמואל דאמר אנא דאמרי
אפילו כתנא קמא, U'shmuel d'amar ana d'amri afilu k'tana kama, I that
say by a boat you have to move the whole thing, I
would say by an animal even a little bit. עד כאן לא
קאמר תנא קמא אלא בבעלי חיים. Ad kan lo ka'amar tana kama
ela biv'alei chayim. Why does he say by the, that a little
bit is enough? That's by an animal. דכיון דמיעקרא יד ורגל, De'keivan
d'me'akrai yad varegel, so here it becomes the fact that it's alive,
once it started moving a front and a hind leg, אידך מיעקרא
קאי, Idach me'akrai kai, it's going to finish taking its step and
it's going to continue to move, so that's like the whole thing
has been displaced. אבל ספינה, Aval sevina, but by an inanimate object,
אי משכה כולה אין אי לא לא, Ei mashchei kula in ei
lo lo, if you do the whole thing, yes, if not, no.
Okay. So that's interesting. But the boat is the fundamental principle of
do you need it to be fully displaced or a little displaced?
And then the question is how do we then apply it to
an animal which has different factors to consider. Yes, Michal.
Clearly some people had animals and some people didn't.
All right. So maybe that's part of it. Maybe some people had
boats. No, I hear your point. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now that was the, now we're going to move beyond,
although that's really interesting and very concrete how physically you have to
move it, we're now going to shift tracks to a much more
abstract issue that that sort of is going to be, you know,
trying to sort of demonstrate this thing but it's going to lead
us elsewhere. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא כהני תנאי, Leima k'hanei
tanna'ei, let's say this debate about full or partial is linked to
the, is linked to the following debate. דתניא, De'tania, we taught a
ברייתא, Baraita, okay, and this is again in קידושין, Kiddushin, this is
where all the קניינים kinyanim exist. ספינה נקנית במשיכה, Sefina nikneis bimeshika,
a boat is acquired by משיכה meshika as we just said. רבי
נתן אומר ספינה ואותיות נקנות במשיכה ובשטר, Rebbi Natan omer sefina v'osios
niknas bimeshika b'shtar,
a boat and letters, okay, I'll say what that means in a
minute,
are acquired with משיכה meshika and שטר. shtar. So there's a lot
of questions here. First of all what does letters mean?
Number two when he says משיכה meshika and שטר shtar does he
mean you need to do both or does he mean either? Okay
but first let's talk about what the word letters means. Letters the
גמרא's Gemara going to understand means a שטר. shtar. You want to
acquire a debt. I'm selling Michael, right, Dov here owes me a
thousand dollars, I'm having a really hard time getting him to pay,
I want to cut my losses, so I'm going to sell that
to Michael for five hundred dollars and then Michael you can collect
the whole thousand because then he'll pay. Okay, so that's what I
do, I sell my debt to, what Dov owes me I sell
that to Michael. Okay, actually we'll say Gloria owes it to me
so there aren't too many Dovs going on here. All right. So
the question here is, how does Michael take possession of that debt?
The money is owed to me personally. What is the way in
which you can transfer this abstract debt? So that's like a real
interesting question. One way you might think you want to do it
is you might transfer the liens. I have liens on Gloria's property,
I'll transfer those liens to Michael. Okay, תוספות Tosafot raises that question.
Because the גמרא Gemara really, really ignores that possibility. It might ignore
that possibility because the liens only operate in conjunction with the personal
obligation with the personal debt. You can't have liens on Gloria's property
if she doesn't owe you the money. Now, the problem with that
is that
somebody could die and the heirs could exercise the liens and get
payment of the debt even when there's no personal debt to the
heirs. But anyway, but one way about doing it would be thinking
about selling the liens instead of selling the debt. That does not
seem to be the way the גמרא Gemara goes because anyway you
could sell a debt even without liens. So what we're somehow doing
is we're transferring this abstract debt itself. So how does that work?
Okay, so one way to think about that which is that Gloria
still owes me the money, but what I basically do is I
sort of give Michael the right to sort of obligate myself or
give Michael the right essentially, we sort of like set up a
direct deposit, okay, so that as soon as Gloria pays me the
money, the money directly goes to Michael. All right, but fundamentally she
still owes me the money. Now, somehow because you're the ultimate end
receiving of that money, you can still bring her to דין, Din,
which raises interesting questions and so on. Okay, but an interesting נפקא
מינא Nafka mina of conceptualizing it that way is that if I
were to actually forgive Gloria the debt after I sold it to
Michael, he'd be left holding the bag, now the empty bag of
money, because fundamentally she still owes me the money and therefore I'm
in a position to forgive the debt. Maybe he wants to come
and sue me, that's a question about גרמא Grama or גרמי, Garmi,
but that's one opinion we're not going to deal with directly here
of שמואל, Shmuel, that even after I sell a debt I can
go ahead and waive it. The other way somehow to conceptualize that
we don't make it so personal just because I lent her the
money she owes it to me, it's more abstract, there's this abstract
thing out there called a debt and I can somehow transfer that.
But that first you have to sort of figure out before you
get to the mechanics of what's the קנין, Kinyan, what does it
mean conceptually to transfer a debt? That's the issue that's really... the
גמרא Gemara doesn't really have... the גמרא Gemara doesn't deal with pure
abstraction so much, it needs things to be more concrete. Like Eli
was just talking the other day about can you own shares in
a corporation, is that like that has חמץ, Chametz, is that like
owning חמץ, Chametz, right? The גמרא Gemara doesn't know about corporations, it
knows about partnerships, it knows about concrete types of things. Anyway, that's
one question is what do you transfer when you, one minute, when
you transfer a debt. But the other question is what is the
physical way in which you do it? So because this is something
abstract, therefore that's why they use the word אותיות. Otiot. If I
have this שטר Shtar here that says Gloria owes me a thousand
dollars and I give Michael this שטר, Shtar, all he got for
himself was a piece of paper. As the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, he can use it as a bottle stopper. יישר כח.
Shkoyach. The physical concrete thing you have here you קונה Koneh with
משיכה, Meshicha, okay, but the physical concrete piece of paper with some
ink on it is worthless. What you don't want is the physical
paper, you want this paper to represent the debt, or in other
words to represent what is written in the paper. So you're not
concerned with the paper and the ink, you're concerned with what's written
in it, what it represents. So that's referred to as אותיות, Otiot,
the letters, meaning the debt that is expressed in this שטר. Shtar.
How are we going to transfer it? And that's going to be
our focus for today is what is the physical way in which
you transfer a debt? It's probably not enough just to take physical
possession of the שטר Shtar because then it only represents the piece
of paper and we want it to represent the debt, meaning the
אותיות. Otiot. Yes, Dov, you had a question?
I just want to clarify something that seems really simple that I'm
missing. Okay, so if Michael owes you money... right... Gloria...
no, Gloria owes me money, let's not get things confused. Gloria owes
you money, right,
and there
were liens
that
I have on Gloria's property.
Right, so that can't just be transferred? So that's what תוספות Tosafot
asks, why not just transfer the liens, why do you have to
transfer the debt? So I said there's two... I only gave one
answer. One answer is that liens don't exist in the context without
them being liens on a debt and the personal obligation still has
to be there. But the other explanation that תוספות Tosafot says is
I don't own the land enough to sell it. So even though
I have liens, I don't have enough ability in ownership of that
property to sell the property or to sell my rights in the
property.
And that's why you kept on problematizing transferring a lien in order
to satisfy a debt with some other third party?
Well, yeah, you can't, but
we
don't conceptualize selling a debt as transferring a lien. First of all,
if we did, it wouldn't work in cases where there was no
lien, where there was no land, but second of all, we don't
conceptualize it that way and the question is why not, which is
a question תוספות Tosafot raises. So there's right, so there's two answers,
either because liens only exist in the context where you owe the
person money, they don't, you can't have a lien
on... meaning they are separate things but they require the law... larger
context of money being owed for the liens to be meaningful. Or
תוספות Tosafos says you just don't have the power to transfer liens
because you don't own enough of the property since you don't own
the property itself. It's only like this abstract right in the property
or quasi ownership of the property, then therefore you're not able to
transfer it.
And the actual owner of the property be מקנה makne you the
loan so to satisfy some other, like can they give you that
lien?
I don't understand what you're saying. I already have the lien. I
don't get it. I'm going to have to... I don't want to
get us off track too much. Okay.
Regardless though, once we get around that, it is transferred with these
liens from the time that you had them. It's not like a
new...
Yeah, that's correct. When I transfer the glorious debt to you, you're
able to... you have rights to those liens, the same rights that
I had to them. Exactly, exactly. Yeah. Nothing's changed. Correct, correct.
What's the point of making this distinction between the letters on a
piece of paper and the piece of paper?
Because you need a different קנין kinyan for,
for example, if I dropped my שטר shtar and it was... and
I lost it and I said, אוי, oy, that's it, I'm never
going to find that שטר shtar again, I'm מיאש miyaish or whatever,
and then you found it. Does Gloria now owe you the money?
No. There's a difference between owning the piece of paper, which you
would own if this was an אבידה aveida that you found, and
owning the debt. So when I transfer it willingly to do a
קנין kinyan on the piece of paper, go ahead and do an
הגבהה, hagbah, do a משיכה, meshicha, do whatever you want. But that's
not necessarily the קנין kinyan that works to transfer the debt that
it represents. Okay.
So, let's take a look.
So, ספינה נקנית במשיכה רבי נתן אומר ספינה ואותיות נקנית במשיכה ובשטר.
Sfinah niknas bemeshicha Rabbi Nasan omer sfinah ve'osyos niknas bemeshicha uveshtar. So
a boat and a debt, letters, are acquired with משיכה meshicha and
a שטר, shtar, maybe it means or שטר, shtar, we'll see. Let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. אותיות? Osyos? So the
גמרא Gemara first says what we have to make sense of this
is a weird ברייתא. braisa. First of all, רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan
introduces this אותיות osyos that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma wasn't talking
about. אותיות מאן דכר שמייהו? Osyos man dchar shemaiyu? Whoever mentioned אותיות,
osyos, whoever mentioned a debt that רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan would be
responding to it? חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Chisuri mechasra vehachi katani. Must
be missing some words and here's how you have to read it.
ספינה נקנית במשיכה ואותיות במסירה. Sfinah niknas bemeshicha ve'osyos bemesirah. We'll read
into the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma a position about שטר shtar so
that we can have רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan responding to that position.
So we read into the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that he says
a שטר shtar is acquired with מסירה. mesirah. So there's our מסירה
mesirah friend again. I'll get back to that. But the point is
where you might say we're making this up out of whole cloth,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said nothing about שטר. shtar. But we're
going to see later another ברייתא braisa where there's an opinion that
שטר shtar is acquired or a debt is acquired by מסירה. mesirah.
So since we know that opinion exists, we're reading it into the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So we're having the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
say a position about a debt to allow רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan
to respond to it. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is going
to say a debt is acquired by מסירה. mesirah. Okay. ורבי
נתן אומר ספינה ואותיות נקנית במשיכה ובשטר. VeRabbi Nasan omer sfinah ve'osyos
niknas bemeshicha uveshtar. Nope, sorry, they are required משיכה meshicha and a
שטר shtar both for a boat and for a debt. So now
he's arguing on both points of the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So
now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that can't be how you
read רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan either, because שטר לספינה למה לי? shtar
lesfinah lamah li? A שטר shtar by a boat, what's its purpose?
You don't have a שטר shtar by cattle. Now of course again,
if you're selling the Queen Anne, the cruise ship or whatever, you
probably do it with a שטר. shtar. But if you're selling a...
but we're not distinguishing, so we're treating it as cattle. So obviously
the שטר shtar is not for the boat. אלא לאו הכי קתני.
Ela lav hachi katani. So now that we change the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, here's how you have to reread רבי נתן. Rabbi Nasan.
ספינה נקנית במשיכה ואותיות במסירה. Sfinah niknas bemeshicha ve'osyos bemesirah.
So first thing it... we are repeating what we said before. We're
introducing into the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma a position about a debt
in order to have רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan respond to it. So
he says a boat you get with משיכה. meshicha. If you want
to transfer a debt, a שטר shtar you have to do it
with משיכה. meshicha. רבי נתן אומר ספינה במשיכה. Rabbi Nasan omer sfinah
bemeshicha.
So now we're splitting the משיכה meshicha and the שטר shtar of
רבי נתן. Rabbi Nasan. A boat I agree to you it's with
משיכה, meshicha, but ואותיות בשטר. ve'osyos beshtar. If you want to transfer
actually a שטר, shtar, you need another שטר shtar to transfer it.
So now what we have is we've...
transfer that שטר shtar though? Okay.
Well, whatever. Anyway,
we have both of them agreeing that a ספינה sfinah is with
משיכה meshicha and they're really debating selling a debt where תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says מסירה mesirah and רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan says a
שטר. shtar. All right, now I'll get back... let's just wrap up
the ספינה sfinah point and then we can shift our attention to
the שטר, shtar, which is going to be the focus. So the
גמרא Gemara says ספינה במשיכה היינו תנא קמא. sfinah bemeshicha hainu Tanna
Kamma. The way we've reread this ברייתא, braisa, both the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan are agreeing that a boat
is with משיכה. meshicha. So what... so why are they both talking
about the boat? אלא דרבה ושמואל איכא בינייהו. Ela deRabbah uShmuel ika
beinaihu. Let's say what they're debating is how much of a משיכה.
meshicha. One of them holds a little bit and the other holds
the full amount. So we get all of that
convoluted rereading of the ברייתא braisa to get to a point that
they both seem to be agreeing about a boat and yet they
seem to be arguing. So must be that they're arguing on the
parameters of משיכה meshicha like רבה. Rabbah. and שמואל. Shmuel. So isn't
that what's going on there? לא, Lo, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא איכא
רב וכשמואל. De'chulei alma ikka Rav u'che'Shmuel. Everybody,
we don't know how they hold. Either they hold like רב, Rav,
a little bit, or like שמואל, Shmuel, the entire amount. That's not
what they're—they're really not debating the boat. Okay. והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar,
this is what they're saying, they, רבי נתן, Rebbi Natan, תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, here's רבי נתן Rebbi Natan speaking to תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. Okay. בספינה מודינא לך, Bis'fina modeini lach, you know what, you
said a boat is משיכה, Meshicha, I agree, boat's משיכה, Meshicha, I
have nothing to debate about that. באותיות, Be'osyot, but when it comes
to selling a debt—I'm sorry, did I skip lines?—now, באותיות, be'osyot, when
it comes to selling a debt, איכא שטר אין אי לא לא,
ikka shtar in, i'lo lo, there you need a שטר, Shtar, there
מסירה Mesira is not going to be enough. Okay. Now, so in
the end of the day, we're saying they could have just discussed
the שטר. Shtar. Okay. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma started with the
statement about a boat and a שטר, Shtar, רבי נתן Rebbi Natan
basically said I concede the point about the boat, but I really
take serious issue with you about the issue about selling a debt.
So we've now bracketed and moved on from רב Rav and שמואל,
Shmuel, they're not debating the issue of a boat. Now what we've
done though is introduced a very serious debate about how do you
sell a debt. So let me say something about the two possibilities
that have been put out here now, which is מסירה Mesira and
שטר Shtar and the logic between it. So why מסירה? Mesira? How
is מסירה Mesira better than let's say משיכה Meshicha or הגבהה? Hagbaha?
Well this is what I said a minute ago. If you go
ahead and you משיכה Meshicha and הגבהה Hagbaha are sort of speak
on the by themselves, by the physical reality. I've lifted this up,
this shows that I control it. I pulled this to me, this
shows I control it. That works by a מציאה. Metzia. Of course
what are you showing that you control? A piece of paper. So
משיכה Meshicha doesn't mean anything when you're trying to transfer the debt.
מסירה Mesira remember does not work by a מציאה, Metzia, מסירה Mesira
is not about the physical control itself, it's about the act of
handing it over. So if I hand over to David there this
שטר Shtar that says Gloria owes me a thousand dollars, that says
more than he owns the piece of paper. Given what's written in
the שטר Shtar and the owner of it is handing it over,
that can be very much symbolically that I am transferring the debt.
Okay, so just physically taking the piece of paper is about the
piece of paper, but handing over the piece of paper is a—can
be a symbolic transfer of a debt. That's מסירה. Mesira. שטר Shtar
makes even more sense because שטר Shtar is saying if David now
is the one to whom Gloria owes the money, you need some
document that says it. The fact that David is holding onto a
document that says Gloria owes me the money does—so since when does
that make him the guy who has the right to collect the
debt? Right? David is going to need another document. And that other
document is going to be—has to be like a-tapped, affixed to this
one and say, Dov sells David Gloria's debt, Gloria now owes the
money to David, Dov is transferring to David all of the right
he has in Gloria's property and all—at, you know, and the entire
debt, and then we hand this original document plus the, you know,
clarifying document on top of it, and that really makes a statement
that I've transferred the debt to David and David now has the
rights to that debt. Yes.
So by מסירה Mesira can it be even let's say it's on
the table and you just say, Alright Michael, here—here it is, I'm
transferring it to you, I don't have—so you don't have to actually
put it anywhere and I don't have to lift it up?
No, you do have to pick—you have to hold onto it. I
have to hold onto it. Yeah, that's מסירה. Mesira.
But מסירה Mesira I don't have to lift up to a
required
distance?
Correct. Well, what's the difference between משיכה Meshicha and מסירה Mesira practically?
I have to still lift it up?
No, משיכה Meshicha you have to move it, מסירה Mesira you just
have to hold it.
So he puts it in my hand? Yeah. But he can't leave
it on the table then say, Michael, it's yours?
No, that's not מסירה. Mesira. מסירה Mesira is—even if the verbal, meaning
we discussed before whether מסירה Mesira requires the physical handing or the
verbal handing over, but even if the verbal handing over suffices at
my end of the one who's transferring it, the receiver has to
physically take hold. מסירה, Mesira, okay, מסירה Mesira requires the physical taking
hold at the receiver's end. Question? Yeah. Okay. Alright. So that's—so now
we understand very well conceptually why the two possibilities are מסירה Mesira
or שטר. Shtar. So now let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara continues because the גמרא's Gemara going to actually say that possibly
the שטר Shtar position is a combination of the two. So let's
take a look. לימא ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי. Leima u'v'pligta d'hani tannai. So
this debate now that we've created between רבי Rebbi and רבי נתן
Rebbi Natan reflects the following debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, De'tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. Braita. אותיות נקנות במסירה דברי רבי. Osyot niknot
b'mesira, divrei Rebbi. רבי Rebbi says אותיות, Osyot, I said רבי נתן,
Rebbi Natan, I meant תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי נתן. Rebbi
Natan. Here's רבי. Rebbi. Okay. אותיות Osyot are acquired with מסירה Mesira
alone, that's what רבי Rebbi says.
וחכמים אומרים, Ve'chachamim omrim, and the Sages say, בין כתב ולא מסר
בין מסר ולא כתב, bein katav v'lo masar, bein masar v'lo katav,
whether you handed it without a writing a new document that said
you were transferring all of the liens and the whole debt, or
you wrote the document without handing it over, לא קני, lo kanai,
you do not take possession, עד שיכתוב וימסור. ad she'yichtov v'yimsor. You
need both. Now why you need the שטר Shtar as we said
makes a lot of sense. So it shouldn't look like David just
owns a piece of paper. It has to be clear.
Why—why is a שטר Shtar itself not enough? Why is it not
enough that I just write a שטר Shtar and say, I am
hereby... Why does it also need the physical handing of the document?
So you could explain this sort of symbolically and you could explain
this just technically. So by what I mean by technically is, is
that שטר shtar it has a very limited scope. שטר shtar by
itself operates only for קרקע karka and slaves or people like a
גט get or קידושין kiddushin or whatever. Okay, שטר shtar does not
operate by something abstract like מטלטלין metaltelin or by something abstract like
a debt. So therefore the שטר shtar cannot by itself have the
power, cannot be the instrument to transfer ownership because a שטר shtar
only transfers land and people and people's status. It doesn't transfer debts.
So what transfers by something that is not people or land is
something like מסירה, mesira, a physical act and so on. But for
that מסירה mesira to be meaningful, to say what that מסירה mesira
is about, it needs the שטר shtar as a clarifying document. Alright,
so you know, but it's not the שטר shtar operating as a
שטר קנין. shtar kinyan. The שטר shtar is operating as a clarifying
document of what this מסירה mesira means. So that's the sort of
technical explanation, which is that a שטר shtar just doesn't have the
ability to serve as an instrument to transfer a debt. What it
can do here is it can clarify what the מסירה mesira means.
I guess the symbolic explanation would be that if I give David
a שטר shtar that says I'm transferring to him the money that
Gloria owes me, but I still hold on to and am holding
on to the original document that says Gloria owes me the money,
well that obviously creates a little bit of a problem, right? Which
is that you know that he now has it to say I
transferred and I'm still holding on to this. So symbolically, it's not
enough to write a שטר shtar that says I'm transferring without also
adding something, the symbolic giving of it, which is sort of symbolized
by this document that says she owes me the money and I'm
going to symbolically give it to him. To say it while keeping
the document for myself, not sort of reinforcing it by the symbolic
handing over, would itself not suffice. So that's why you need both
the שטר shtar and the מסירה. mesira. But again, conceptually, I think
the best way to understand it is that the שטר shtar is
not the instrument of transfer. The מסירה mesira is the instrument of
transfer, but so that it should be clear that you're not transferring
the paper, but you're transferring the debt, what you need is the
שטר shtar to clarify and to make that statement, to create that
context.
Okay, I don't understand the מחלוקת machlokes between רבי Rebbi and the
חכמים. Chachamim.
Really? I just spent five minutes explaining it.
I understand everything you just said, but I don't see it in
the words.
I'm just trying to give background explanation. All they're saying is רבי
Rebbi says you need to do מסירה, mesira, and the חכמים Chachamim
say מסירה mesira and a שטר. shtar.
Right? That you see?
Yeah, a hundred percent.
So I'm trying to explain what conceptually מסירה mesira does and what
the combination of מסירה mesira and שטר shtar does.
I'm just missing one small piece. Right, but unless you're missing one
screw, go, go, go ahead.
What, when רבי Rebbi says you need מסירה, mesira, what's he being
מוסר? moseir? Is he not being מוסר moseir a written document? He
is. So the חכמים Chachamim are also being that...
oh, you mean the... no, the חכמים Chachamim are saying מסירה mesira
is required but is not sufficient. רבי Rebbi says just מסירה mesira
does it, and the חכמים Chachamim say only the combination of מסירה
mesira and
שטר. shtar. And so when רבי Rebbi says,
all you need is מסירה mesira according to רבי. Rebbi. Right. Is
that verbal? I mean...
No, classic מסירה. mesira. Maybe I complicated things too much by my
earlier discussion on מסירה. mesira. Classic מסירה mesira is I'm handing it
over. Right. That's not verbal, that's the physical handing over.
But as an original as opposed to creating a new one that
says here...
oh, was that the confusion? Right.
מסירה mesira of the שטר. shtar. שטר shtar is not, thank you
Gloria, שטר shtar is not the original שטר. shtar. שטר shtar is
an additional document that clarifies and that states that you are transferring
over the loan.
So when the חכמים Chachamim say מסירה mesira and כתיבה, kesiva, they
mean two שטרות. shtaros.
Well, one new one and yes, the מסירה mesira of the old
שטר shtar and a כתיבה kesiva of a new one. Correct.
So two pieces of parchment for the חכמים Chachamim and only one
for רבי. Rebbi. Yes.
That. Okay. Alright, so good. I'm glad we clarified that.
And I would wager that that probably helped someone else.
I'm sure it did. Okay. Fine. Great. Okay. Alright, I have no
problem, great. Okay. So that's right. So רבי Rebbi says it's the
handing over of the original document, and the חכמים Chachamim says that
it is that you need that does not suffice, you need two
things. You need the handing over of the original document plus the
writing of a new document that is saying what you are doing.
Okay, so for רבי Rebbi the handing of the original document shows
the act of transfer of the debt, and the חכמים Chachamim say
no, no, no, it's not symbolically enough to hand it, you need
something to declare that's what you're doing. So you need a second
document to make it clear that's what's happening. Okay? So that's the
debate. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: במאי אוקימתא?
B'mai okimta? So now the debate of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
and רבי נתן, Rebbi Nasan, which is מסירה mesirah or מסירה ושטר,
mesirah v'shtar, רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan said שטר shtar but we're going
to read it to mean מסירה mesirah and שטר, shtar, is the
same debate of רבי Rebbi and the חכמים. Chachamim. Fine. Now במאי
אוקימתא B'mai okimta to רבי? Rebbi? Now
במאי אוקימתא B'mai okimta to רבי? Rebbi? So you said now that
the רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan who said, wait, let me just make
sure I got this right. Oh, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of
רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan who said ספינה במשיכה sfina b'meshicha held that
a שטר shtar was with מסירה. mesirah. So you made the... my
thing, we have to write this.
The horse moves.
ספינה במשיכה, sfina b'meshicha,
אותיות במסירה. otiot b'mesirah. That's what we reread into the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. And רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan said ספינה במשיכה sfina b'meshicha
because they're not debating that. That's how we got here. And אותיות
otiot are בשטר. b'shtar. But when we say בשטר, b'shtar, in order
to... well here, let's leave that for a minute. Okay, that's ברייתא
braisa number one. ברייתא braisa number two is רבי Rebbi says במסירה.
b'mesirah.
Okay, so that's the same.
And who was the other one? Oh, and the חכמים. Chachamim. The
חכמים Chachamim say מסירה mesirah plus כתיבה. ktiva.
מסירה mesirah plus כתיבה ktiva of a new שטר. shtar. Okay? So
that's the שטר shtar part here is the כתיבה ktiva part. And
we're going to assume that when רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan says שטר,
shtar, in order to make it the same as the חכמים, Chachamim,
it means שטר shtar plus מסירה. mesirah. Okay? So that's how we've
lined this up. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so you're saying
that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
here,
you're saying the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here is רבי. Rebbi. רבי
Rebbi says a שטר shtar is מסירה. mesirah. That's the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. So that means that רבי Rebbi would be saying, if
we're identifying these positions, then רבי Rebbi would presumably would also be
saying that a boat is with משיכה. meshicha. So let's see if
that works. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says במאי אוקימתא? B'mai okimta?
Where
are we? כרבי. K'Rebbi. Like רבי. Rebbi. ספינה נמי תקני במסירה? Sfina
nami tikni b'mesirah? So why, if this תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who
says אותיות במסירה otiot b'mesirah is רבי, Rebbi, why does he say
a ספינה sfina has to be משיכה? meshicha? We know elsewhere that
רבי Rebbi should say that a ספינה sfina would be enough to
do מסירה, mesirah, which has got to be a lot easier
than moving the boat. Just like hand over, I don't know, some
of the ropes or something. Okay. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braisa: ספינה נקנית במסירה דברי רבי. sfina niknis b'mesirah divrei Rebbi.
רבי Rebbi says you can do it with מסירה. mesirah. וחכמים אומרים:
לא קנה עד שימשכנה Vechachamim omrim lo kana ad sheyimshachena. או עד
שישכור מקומה. No, sorry.
מסירה mesirah does not work. You have to actually drag it to
you or you have to rent out its space. If you own,
if it's in a dock let's say. Actually, that's funny because actually
it's not where... it's not sort of the dock that's around it.
You'd have to own the water underneath it. So you know, you
go ahead and your boat is in a pond, a private owned
pond that you have in your backyard. So you would have to
go ahead and if you rented out the pond to the guy
you were selling the boat to, then the boat would be now
in a pond that this other guy is temporarily owning. So that's
a קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. Your object's in my domain. Well no,
not אגב. agav.
אגב מים? Agav mayim?
Yeah but no, this is חצר. chatzer. This is חצר. chatzer. If
you... your object is in my field and you want to sell
it to me, I can take possession of it. So if you
rent me your pond and now the boat you're trying to sell
me is in the pond that I have currently rented, I take
possession. It's a type of קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So the חכמים
Chachamim say מסירה mesirah does not work. You want to get the
boat? You gotta move it. Or if the guy can sell you
the water or rent you the water that it's sitting in, then
that's... or if it's dry-docked, rents you the space that it's dry-docked
in, then that's another way. But sorry, מסירה mesirah does not work.
So רבי Rebbi introduces that מסירה mesirah works by a boat. So
if this תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is רבי, Rebbi, why does he
only say משיכה? meshicha? He should also be saying מסירה. mesirah. Okay,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So the גמרא Gemara says: By the
way, you understand, I mean, there's a whole question why should מסירה,
mesirah, what should be the debate? Like if you remember going back
to קידושין, Kiddushin, משיכה meshicha works by everything. מסירה mesirah has a
more limited scope. מסירה mesirah is like by large animals, like by
a cow, a horse, or now we're discussing does it work by
a boat? So one of the reasons that מסירה mesirah should maybe
work by those is because משיכה meshicha is harder. Now, I mean,
like certainly in the boat case. I mean, I don't know if
משיכה meshicha is that hard by a horse, a horse is regularly
moved or whatever, but certainly maybe at least
conceptually, I don't know. But so one thing is to think maybe
somehow it's harder to do משיכה... meshicha... works in the boat more
than in the other cases, or somehow that מסירה mesira is more
symbolically meaningful. There's an idea of handing over the reins, handing over
something is more symbolically meaningful by something like a horse or by
something like a boat than it would maybe be by I don't
know, a sheep or something. But it's not exactly clear why מסירה
mesira is limited to certain types of objects. We discussed why it
was very important by a שטר shtar because by a שטר shtar
you need the symbolism of transfer. It's not enough to focus on
the physical object. It's not as clear why מסירה mesira should be
limited to בהמה גסה behema gassa and maybe to boats, but that's
what we're debating. Does ספינה sfina work by a boat or not?
So since רבי Rebbe says מסירה mesira works by a boat, then
and here you're anyway we've introduced that תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
talking about מסירה, mesira, why doesn't he mention מסירה mesira there as
well?
Yes. This concept of a קניין חצר, kinyan chatzer, does the person
who's renting you the property and that has the boat on it,
does he have to have intention that he's giving you that boat
as well?
Yeah, you can't buy something, take something from somebody if he's not
trying to transfer it.
Even if you've rented it doesn't...
Right, of course. Okay, so of course it must be לא קשיא
lo kashya so it's not difficult. כאן ברשות הרבים כאן בסימטא. Kan
birshut harabbim kan besimta. Ah, here's a story. Here we are talking
about you're trying to sell the thing in a רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim. So in a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, משיכה meshikha does not
work. So how does משיכה meshikha work? משיכה meshikha works by saying
I'm taking it to me, it's now under my control. So in
a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, which is like, you know, Time Square
whatever, if something isn't like in your pocket or on your body
or whatever, it isn't in your control. All right? So משיכה meshikha
only works in a place which is semi-private.
משיכה meshikha works if we go to let's say some side alley,
okay? Where it's quiet or whatever, something called a סימטא, simta, there
if I pull something to me because it's not as busy and
whatever, it's like right now I can say that I'm like under
my control, the act of pulling makes it sort of under my
control. It does not work in רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. Whereas מסירה,
mesira, remember, is the symbolic act of transfer. It's not just about
the physical control. So since it's about the symbolic act of transfer,
for example, like חליפין chalupin would work in a רשות הרבים, reshut
harabbim, right? The קניין סודר. kinyan sudar. It's all about the symbolic
act of transfer. So that works in a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
but משיכה meshikha which is about the physical control over it, that
works only in a sort of an alley, not in a רשות
הרבים. reshut harabbim. So here we're talking about a רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim and here we're talking about a סימטא. simta. So therefore here
מסירה mesira works, משיכה meshikha does not work. Here, now here's the
interesting thing.
I get that משיכה meshikha does work in a סימטא, simta, but
why doesn't מסירה mesira also work in a סימטא? simta? Right? In
רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, I just got through telling you משיכה's meshikha
not meaningful. The only thing that can work is מסירה. mesira. Here
it's a סימטא. simta. Okay, I get that now משיכה meshikha can
work, but what happened to מסירה? mesira? Why not also say מסירה?
mesira? So this leads to a fascinating discussion in the ראשונים, rishonim,
which is, is there a hierarchy of קניינים? kinyanim? And קניינים kinyanim
some קניינים kinyanim are more symbolic, more meaningful, better seen generally as
better than others. And therefore, if you can do the better one,
the weaker one doesn't work. So that's the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
and a number of ראשונים rishonim say it. Since you're in a
סימטא simta and you can do משיכה, meshikha, only משיכה meshikha works,
מסירה mesira does not work. To which רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam has
a great line, and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says, וכי קניינים מצות
הן שאין לעשות אלא מן המובחר? Vechi kinyanim mitzvot hen she-ein la-asot
ella min hamuvchar?
which is like, are קניינים kinyanim like a מצוה mitzvah that you
can only do the best קניין? kinyan? Not if a קניין kinyan
works, it works. What does it mean just because I have an
option of doing משיכה meshikha I shouldn't be able to do מסירה?
mesira? Why does the opportunity to do another one void the meaning
of this one? If מסירה mesira works, let it work. Okay, it's
מהדרין. mehadrin. Anyway, so I'm not going to get into how they
fully unpack that, but that's the basic answer of the גמרא. Gemara.
מסירה mesira which is about transfer works in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
משיכה meshikha that's about control does not. So here משיכה meshikha is
not mentioned. Here where it's a סימטא, simta, משיכה meshikha is mentioned.
Okay, so let's read that. כאן ברשות הרבים כאן בסימטא. Kan birshut
harabbim kan besimta. ורמינהו אוקימתא. Varminhu okimta. What do you say we're
talking about? להא בתרייתא, Le'ha batraita, this second ברייתא braita here. Number
two. ברשות הרבים, Birshut harabbim, the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and therefore
it's only מסירה mesira not משיכה. meshikha. So אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
let's look at the end. וחכמים אומרים Ve-Chachamim omrim: לא קנה עד
שימשכנה. So the חכמים chachamim say in this
oh wait a minute, I put this thing here. This is the
שטר shtar thing. I'm sorry, we actually need a third column.
This was the parallel to the שטר, shtar, all of this is
about שטר, shtar, right? So that's all about שטר. shtar. That's our
focus. And then here you have the whole ספינה sfina ברייתא braita
that we're now talking about. Right? Where רבי Rebbe said ספינה sfina
is with מסירה. mesira. Okay, we're lined up. lining all these things
up and the who was it the חכמים Chachamim say
חכמים Chachamim say חכמים Chachamim say משיכה Meshichah or שכירת מקום. Sechirat
Makom. שכירת מקום. Sechirat Makom. So now we have said, I put
the thing this way about the שטר. Shtar. Anyway here we're saying
this is רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So here, it's all, this is
all רבי, Rebbi, okay? So here he says מסירה Mesirah and here
he says משיכה Meshichah because this is רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim משיכה
Meshichah doesn't work, and this is a סמטא Simta so משיכה Meshichah
does work. Fine. And that's why this only says משיכה Meshichah this
says מסירה Mesirah by the boat. But now he's got a problem.
If this is רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim then how can they say
oh no מסירה Mesirah doesn't work you've got to do משיכה Meshichah
you have to rent where it's sitting? Neither of those work in
רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. משיכה Meshichah doesn't work like we just said,
and you can't rent a space, you don't own the space. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. ברשות הרבים אימא סיפא וחכמים אומרים
לא קנה עד
שימשכנה BeReshus Harabbim eima seifa veChachamim omrim lo kana ad sheyimshachenah ואי
ברשות הרבים ve'ei beReshus Harabbim if you're in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim
ממאן אוגיר? mi-man ogir? Who are you going to rent the space
from? You can't rent out the space. ותו משיכה ברשות הרבים מי
קניא? Vesu Meshichah beReshus Harabbim mi kanya? And how could they say
משיכה Meshichah works? Your whole point was to say since we're in
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim it's only מסירה Mesirah not משיכה. Meshichah. So
how could the חכמים Chachamim be saying משיכה Meshichah works in רשות
הרבים? Reshus Harabbim?
משיכה Meshichah won't work in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim because this thing
won't move in...
No, no. What I said before is that the act of demonstrating
control, physical control, is not meaningful in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. If
you took it on your body, but that would be like הגבהה.
Hagbahah. But something's on the ground and you drag it to you,
something on the ground in
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, you're not enough demonstrating control over it. Why?
Because there's everybody's running around. It's like in the middle of Times
Square. I've got my, if I've got, you know, don't leave your
objects unattended. I've got my
little briefcase on the ground in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim and I'm
not holding onto it, I'm not so in control of that briefcase,
let me tell you. Okay?
No, but משיכה Meshichah means you are in control of it. It
just...
No, but it's not as meaningfully demonstrating that when it's in a
רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. The fact that you just dragged it, the
fact that you're not fully holding onto it, that's not very safe
to have your briefcase on the ground and be dragging it in
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim in the sense of protecting and controlling, right?
So the amount that the dragging of it demonstrates control in a
semi-private space, that's one thing, but in a big public space it
does not, so it's not meaningful in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim.
Okay, so you're saying nothing belongs to anybody?
No, it does not mean you don't own what you have. It
means you can't demonstrate that you're taking ownership because it's not a
meaningful, yeah.
But it also means that if somebody else drags your briefcase in
Times Square, they don't own it now.
Well, nobody can own anything unless you want to transfer
it. Okay? I mean, no, no, no. The point is we start
by the fact that you are trying, the owner is trying to
transfer it, you're trying to take it, but what needs to make
that, it's not the act does it in itself. If I go
ahead and I מושך moshech your wallet, I don't own it, I
stole your wallet. I don't own your wallet. It requires a desire
to transfer. But the act that effects the transfer is an act
that symbolizes and signifies ownership and control, and it has to do
it in a meaningful way. So that's why we discussed, is משיכה
Meshichah how much of משיכה Meshichah do you have to do? How
high do you have to be מגביה magbi'ah it? So one of
the questions is in what contexts are you doing it?
So רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim and סמטא Simta are contexts. Yeah, exactly.
So as in a situation that it's not, let's say, a lost
thing, where it's clearly a transferor and a transferee. Right. Why is
מסירה Mesirah not always the better one?
So that is an excellent point because you're saying מסירה Mesirah symbolically
shows transfer. So that's why תוספות Tosafot actually quotes an opinion that's
directly opposite of the רשב"ם Rashbam and says, what are you talking
about? מסירה Mesirah is always the best. Now it doesn't work for
everything. Like we said, for some reason it's limited to large animals
and boats, and why that should be it's not clear. But he
actually says the exact opposite. מסירה Mesirah is he says is more
symbolically meaningful and it works for שטרות Shtarot and משיכה Meshichah doesn't
work for שטרות. Shtarot. So yes, there is that exactly that debate.
Okay, so I don't have a good answer to defend the other
side. All right, so now, so the question was if this is
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, we get why רבי Rebbi said only מסירה
Mesirah not משיכה Meshichah because משיכה Meshichah is not symbolically as meaningful
in that context. But then how do the
חכמים Chachamim say משיכה ושכירות מקום? meshikhah u-sekhirut makom, אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרווייהו, Abaye veRava de'amri tarveihu, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both say,
מסירה קונה ברשות הרבים, Mesirah konah beReshus Harabbim, where מסירה Mesirah works,
boat, שטרות, Shtarot, or cows or whatever, it works
in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, ובחצר שאינו של שניהם, uvechatzer she'eino shel
sheneihem, and in some yard that nobody has rights to, ומשיכה קונה,
uMeshichah konah, but משיכה Meshichah works, which is more global, but that
works by all objects or all chattel, but only בסמטא ובחצר שהיא
של שניהם, beSimta uvechatzer shehi shel sheneihem, only in a place where
you have some semi-rights, an alley that people have that's permitted for
people to use the alley, you're not in somebody else's yard, or
some type of a yard that you both own. And there the
combination of the fact that you have rights to be here... It's
not being overrun by people, it's semi-private, and you drag the thing
towards you, that context makes משיכה Meshichah meaningful. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והגבהה קונה בכל
מקום, ve-hagbahah koneh be-khol makom, הגבהה, hagbahah, right, works everywhere, even if
I'm trying to buy, you know, David's thing on his yard, I
lift it up and I'm standing on his yard, the fact that
I'm lifting the thing up shows my control and my ownership. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
This is a crazy thing, by the way, given what you just
said about context. You come into my backyard, you still need some
חזקה, hazakah, right?
Again, you are, what you're missing is the act does not do
it by itself. I mean, it does by itself by הפקר ואבידה.
hefker va-aveidah. You need the desire to transfer. No thing is being
done against anybody's will. But even with all of that desire, you
need the act to seal the deal and the act has to
have meaning, and therefore context determines meaning. So even if I'm in
your yard, anything that's in my pockets, anything I'm holding up like
this, is something that I'm in full control of even when I'm
on your yard. So therefore the act of lifting it up is
meaningful even in the seller's property. Okay. With the fact that the
seller is selling it. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Now. Okay, מאי עד שימשכנה? mai ad she-yimshakhenah? So now we
said this is רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, so how do we explain
משיכה meshikhah in שכירות מקום? sekhirut makom? מאי עד שימשכנה נמי דקאמר
מאי עד שישכור מקומו דקאמר? mai ad she-yimshakhenah nami de-ka-amar mai ad
she-yiskor mekomo de-ka-amar? No, here's what those words mean. הכי קאמר: hakhi
ka-amar: עד שימשכנה מרשות הרבים לסימטא. ad she-yimshakhenah me-reshut ha-rabim le-simta. So
you're in the רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, רבי Rebbi says, no problem,
do a מסירה, mesirah, מסירה mesirah works. וחכמים va-Hakhamim say, I'm sorry,
we don't like מסירה mesirah by boats. You're in your רשות הרבים,
reshut ha-rabim, you can't do מסירה, mesirah, tough luck. You know what
you're going to have to do? You're going to have to do
a משיכה meshikhah and take it from the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim
and drag it, again, I don't know if this is dry-docked, if
we have a, we're living in Venice or רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim
could be the water, I don't know what we're dealing with, but
you got to drag it from רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim into the
סימטא. simta. So משיכה meshikhah not within רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, but
משיכה meshikhah from רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim to a
סימטא. simta. Okay. ואי משום בעלים היא, ve-i mishum ba'alim hi, and
by the way, if it were רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, if it
was in the owner's property,
then לא קנה עד שישכור מקומו, lo kanah ad she-yiskor mekomo, then
you could go ahead and rent it out. So yes, רבי Rebbi
is talking about רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, when the חכמים Hakhamim say
משיכה meshikhah ושכירות מקום, veSechirat Makom? they're saying I'm sorry, it won't
work in רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and מסירה mesirah won't work, and
if you want to do it, you need to do it in
a different context and you need to do a different type of
a thing.
You cannot sell a boat on the high seas.
You cannot sell a boat on the high seas, you could do
it with חליפין. halifin. That's what's missing. What always works, right, is
we'll just take out my, you know, my handkerchief and do it
with חליפין. halifin. That you could do, right, which is funny, which
is like the easiest thing you would say to do. Okay, but
the actual acts that are physically controlling the boat, right, according to
the חכמים Hakhamim you could not do it on the high seas.
That is correct.
What's the difference between חליפין halifin and מסירה? mesirah?
מסירה mesirah is the object I am myself selling and you're actually
taking physical possession of the object and it also works, the buyer
gives the object over to the seller. So I, you know, so
let's say, you know, so if, so I take the reins of
my horse and I hand you the reins of my horse. Okay.
If now if I want to sell you my horse with חליפין,
halifin, it's the opposite. You give me your pen and by me
taking possession of your pen, you take possession of my horse. Okay,
and then I have to do a קנין, kinyan, well not really
a קנין, kinyan, I just have to hold on. Now does that
cover everything, the חליפין? halifin?
Pretty much. Pretty much, it's just really all
not necessary, but...
Right, I mean what's worth pointing out, right is, we mentioned before
about הלכה halakhah dealing with abstract issues, right? All the קניינים kinyanim
really focus on the concrete, physical control of the object. I mean,
certainly by מטלטלין, metaltelin, by a שטר shtar where you can't physically
control it, well some things you do, you do a חזקה, hazakah,
you try to physically do something on it, right? And okay, שטר,
shtar, whatever, but mostly, certainly by מטלטלין metaltelin it's about physical control.
What חליפין halifin comes and does is חליפין halifin sort of abstracts
the whole thing. Right. And חליפין halifin basically says ignore the physical
object. This is sort of a partly what was bothering Dov. Once
I want to sell you something and we both agree, then let's
just do a, let's just shake hands. So essentially חליפין halifin sort
of works as like a handshake. It just shows our conviction to
do the transaction and it finalizes us. And it's not about the
physical,
you know, object itself and demonstrating that physical control. So they are
very conceptually different types of things.
Right, that's why when we were talking about a debt a little
while ago, which is abstract.
Right, you might want
a second שטר shtar possibly to clarify.
Right, exactly. Exactly, right. Okay, so we will end here. Thankfully tomorrow's
דף daf is also short and we will continue with this discussion
about how do you transfer, now that we've reconciled these ברייתות, braitot,
we're going to go back to focus on transferring a debt and
that'll be our focus for tomorrow.
Yeah, one thing.
Yeah. Oh, tomorrow's...